A Finding Aid to the John White Alexander Papers, 1775-1968, bulk 1870-1915, in the Archives of American Art AAA.alexjohn
Archives of American Art
John White Alexander papers
bulk 1870-1915
1775-1968
AAA.alexjohn
Archives of American Art
11.2 Linear feet
The papers of the painter, muralist, and illustrator John White Alexander measure 11.2 linear feet and date from 1775 to 1968, with the bulk of materials dating from 1870 to 1915. Papers document Alexander's artistic career and many connections to figures in the art world through biographical documentation, correspondence (some illustrated), writings, 13 sketchbooks, additonal artwork and loose sketches, scrapbooks, photographs, awards and medals, artifacts, and other records. Also found is a souvenir engraving of a Mark Twain self-portrait.
Alexander, John White
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Irina Reed, granddaughter of John White Alexander, in 1978 and 1981.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The papers of John White Alexander in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2009-2010, and total 5592 images.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of the original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical/Historical note
John White Alexander was born in 1856 in Allegheny City, Pennsylvania. He was orphaned at age five and taken in by relatives of limited means. When Alexander left school and began working at a telegraph company, the company's vice-president, former civil war Colonel Edward Jay Allen, took an interest in his welfare. Allen became his legal guardian, brought him into the Allen household, and saw that he finished Pittsburgh High School. At eighteen, he moved to New York City and was hired by Harper and Brothers as an office boy in the art department. He was soon promoted to apprentice illustrator under staff artists such as Edwin A. Abbey and Charles Reinhart. During his time at Harpers, Alexander was sent out on assignment to illustrate events such as the Philadelphia Centennial celebration in 1876 and the Pittsburgh Railroad Strike in 1877, which erupted in violence.
Alexander carefully saved money from his illustration work and traveled to Europe in 1877 for further art training. He first enrolled in the Royal Art Academy of Munich, Germany, but soon moved to the village of Polling, where a colony of American artists was at its peak in the late 1870s. Alexander established a painting studio there and stayed for about a year. Despite his absence from the Munich Academy, he won the medal of the drawing class for 1878, the first of many honors. While in Polling, he became acquainted with J. Frank Currier, Frank Duveneck, William Merritt Chase, and other regular visitors to the colony. He later shared a studio and taught a painting class in Florence with Duveneck and traveled to Venice, where he met James Abbott McNeill Whistler.
Alexander returned to New York in 1881 and resumed his commercial artwork for Harpers and Century. Harpers sent him down the Mississippi river to complete a series of sketches. He also began to receive commissions for portraits, and in the 1880s painted Charles Dewitt Bridgman, a daughter of one of the Harper brothers, Parke Godwin, Thurlow Weed, Walt Whitman, and Oliver Wendell Holmes. Alexander met his wife Elizabeth, whose maiden name was also Alexander, through her father, James W. Alexander, who was sometimes mistaken for the artist. Elizabeth and John White Alexander married in 1887 and had a son, James, in 1888.
Alexander and his family sailed for France in 1890, where they became a part of the lively literary and artistic scene in Paris at the time. Among their many contacts there were Puvis de Chavannes, Auguste Rodin, and Whistler, who arrived in Paris shortly thereafter. Alexander absorbed the new aesthetic ideas around him such as those of the symbolists and the decorative style of art nouveau. Critics often note how such ideas are reflected in his boldly composed paintings of women from this period, who titles drew attention to the sensual and natural elements of the paintings. His first exhibition in Paris was three paintings at the Société Nationale des Beaux Arts in 1893, and by 1895 he has become a full member of the Société.
Independent and secession artist societies emerged throughout Europe during this period, and Alexander exhibited with several of them, including the Société Neuvelle in Paris, the Munich Secession, and the Vienna Secession. He was also elected an honorary member of the Royal Society of Belgian Artists and the Royal Society of British Painters in London. His exhibited works sold well, and his influence began to be felt back in the United States. Andrew Carnegie and John Beatty of the Carnegie Institute consulted closely with Alexander in the planning and execution of the first Carnegie International Exhibitions. Alexander also became active in supporting younger American artists who wanted to exhibit in Europe, a stance which resulted in his resignation from the Society of American Artists in Paris, which he felt had become a barrier to younger artists. His promotion of American art became an central aspect of his career for the remainder of his life, most visibly through his presidency of the National Academy of Design from 1909 until shortly before his death in 1915. He also served frequently on juries for high-profile exhibitions, and was a trustee at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the New York Public Library, and the national Institute of Arts and Letters. Around 1912, he helped to form the School Art League in New York, which provided art instruction to high school students.
Alexander returned to the United States nearly every summer while based in Paris, and among his commissioned paintings were murals for the newly-constructed Library of Congress, completed around 1896. In 1901, the Alexanders returned to New York permanently. The demand for portraits continued, and he had his first solo exhibition at the Durand-Ruel Galleries in 1902. Around 1905 he received a commission for murals at the new Carnegie Institute building in Pittsburgh for the astounding sum of $175,000. He created 48 panels there through 1908. During this period, the Alexanders spent summers in Onteora, New York, where Alexander painted his well-known "Sunlight" paintings. There they became friends and collaborators with the actress Maude Adams, with Alexander designing lighting and stage sets, and Elizabeth Alexander designing costumes for Adams' productions such as Peter Pan, the Maid of Orleans, and Chanticleer. The couple became known for their "theatricals" or tableaux, staged at the MacDowell Club and elsewhere, and Elizabeth Alexander continued her design career when her husband died in 1915.
Alexander left several commissions unfinished upon his death at age 59, including murals in Wisconsin, Ohio, and Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. Elizabeth Alexander held a memorial exhibition at Arden Galleries a few months after his death, and a larger memorial exhibition was held by the Carnegie Institute in 1916. Alexander won dozens of awards for artwork in his lifetime, including the Lippincott Prize at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts in 1899, the Gold Medal of Honor at the Paris Exposition Universelle in 1900, the Gold Medal at the Panama Pacific Exposition of 1901, and the Medal of the First Class at the Carnegie Institute International Exhibition in 1911. In 1923, the Alexander Memorial Studio was built at the MacDowell colony in New Hampshire to honor his memory.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of the painter, muralist, and illustrator John White Alexander measure 11.2 linear feet and date from 1775 to 1968, with the bulk of materials dating from 1870 to 1915. Papers document Alexander's artistic career and many connections to figures in the art world through biographical documentation, correspondence (some illustrated), writings, 13 sketchbooks, additonal artwork and loose sketches, scrapbooks, photographs, awards and medals, artifacts, and other records. Also found is a souvenir engraving of a Mark Twain self-portrait.
Biographical Information includes multiple essays related to Alexander, his family, and others in his circle. Also found is an extensive oral history of Alexander's wife Elizabeth conducted in 1928. Correspondence includes letters written by Alexander to his family from New York and Europe at the start of his career, and later letters from fellow artists, art world leaders, and portrait sitters of Alexander's. Significant correspondents include Charles Dana Gibson, Florence Levy, Frederick Remington, Robert Louis Stevenson, Henry James, John La Farge, Francis Davis Millet, and Andrew Carnegie. Correspondence includes some small sketches as enclosures and illustrated letters.
Certificates and records related to Alexander's career are found in Associations and Memberships, Legal and Financial Records, and Notes and Writings, which contain documentation of Alexander's paintings and exhibitions. Scattered documentation of Alexander's memberships in various arts association exists for the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Academy in Rome, the National Academy of Design, the Onteora Club in New York, the Royal Academy of Fine Arts in Munich, Germany, the Ministère de L'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts, the Union Internationale des Beaux Arts et des Lettres, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Notes and Writings include speeches written by Alexander, short stories and essays written by his wife, and articles by various authors about Alexander. Extensive documentation of the planning and construction of the Alexander Memorial Studio by the MacDowell Club is found, along with other awards, medals, and memorial resolutions adopted by arts organizations after Alexander's death.
Artwork includes thirteen sketchbooks with sketches related to Alexander's commercial illustration and cartooning, murals, paintings, and travels. Dozens of loose drawings and sketches are also found, along with two volumes and several dozen loose reproductions of artwork, among which are found fine prints by named printmakers. Many sketches are also interspersed throughout the correspondence. Eight Scrapbooks contain mostly clippings, but also scattered letters, exhbition catalogs, announcements, invitations, and photographs related to Alexander's career between 1877 and 1915. Additional Exhibition Catalogs and later clippings, as well as clippings related to the career of his wife and other subjects, are found in Printed Materials.
Photographs include many portraits of Alexander taken by accomplished photographers such as Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Aimé Dupont, Curtis Bell, Elizabeth Buehrmann, and several signed Miss Huggins, who may have been Estelle Huntington Huggins, a New York painter and photographer. Portraits of others include Alexander's friends William Merritt Chase and Edward Austin Abbey. Also found are photographs of groups, juries, family, friends, and studios in New York, Paris, and New Jersey, and a handful of scenic photographs of Polling, Bavaria, where Alexander had an early studio. A large number of photographs of works of art are found, many with annotations. Among the photographs of murals are a small collection of snapshots of the Carnegie Institute murals in progress. Miscellaneous artifacts include a palette, several printing plates, and an inscribed souvenir engraving of a self-portrait caricature of Mark Twain.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into 11 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1887-1968 (Box 1, OV 23; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1870-1942 (Box 1; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Associations and Memberships, circa 1897-1918 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Legal and Financial Records, 1775, 1896-1923 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, circa 1875-1943 (Boxes 1-2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Awards and Memorials, circa 1870-1944 (Box 2, OV 24; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1875-1915 (Boxes 2-3, 14-16, OV 23; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, circa 1877-1915 (Boxes 17-22; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 9: Printed Materials, circa 1891-1945 (Boxes 3-4, OV 23; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 10: Photographs, circa 1870-1915 (Boxes 4-8, MGP 1-2, OV 25-43, RD 44-45; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 11: Artifacts, circa 1899-1915 (Box 6, artifact cabinet; 0.4 linear feet)
Abbey, Edwin Austin, 1852-1911; Alexander, Elizabeth A., d. 1947; Alexander, John White, 1856-1915; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916; Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944; James, Henry, 1843-1916; La Farge, John, 1835-1910; Levy, Florence N. (Florence Nightingale), 1870-1947; MacDowell Club of New York; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912; Remington, Frederic, 1861-1909; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903; Awards; Illustrators--New York (State)--New York; Interviews; Medals; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Portrait painters--New York (State)--New York; Portrait painting, American; Portrait painting--19th century; Portrait painting--20th century; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Works of art
- Biographical Information, circa 1887-1968; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1, OV 23
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains notes, writings, and printed materials that describe the life of John White Alexander, as well as ephemera and personal documents related to specific life events.
  Notes and narratives include biographical essays about Alexander and his guardian, Colonel Edward Jay Allen, taken from published reference works, and notes made by Elizabeth Alexander in preparation of those entries. Personal documents and ephemera include a wedding invitation, an identity card issued for the Paris International Exposition of 1900, a calling card, a circular about an artist named Jacques Alexander, examples of Alexander's signature, and a French visa. Also found are drafts of essays by Elizabeth Alexander about her husband and others in their circle, and an oral history interview of Elizabeth Alexander in three parts taken by DeWitt M. Lockman, a later president of the National Academy of Design.
  Arrangement note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Biographical Notes and Essays, circa 1913-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Documents and Ephemera, circa 1887-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (Oversized items housed in OV 23)
  - Essays by Elizabeth Alexander about John White Alexander, after 1915; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Essays by Elizabeth Alexander about Others in their Circle, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oral History Interview of Elizabeth Alexander by DeWitt M. Lockman, 1928; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Oversized Personal Documents and Ephemera, circa 1887-1900 (Box 23 (OV))
    Items scanned with Box 1, f2
- Correspondence, circa 1870-1942; Series 2; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains personal and business correspondence of John White Alexander and his wife, Elizabeth Alexander. Correspondence from the 1870s and 1880s consists primarily of Alexander's letters home to his guardian, Colonel Edward Jay Allen, the Allen family, and his friend, E.E. Phelps, all in Pittsburgh, written from New York and Europe. 1876 letters detail his visit to the Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia. Many of these letters are found with typed transcriptions which contain scattered annotations which appear to be in Elizabeth Alexander's handwriting. In a couple of cases, transcripts exist for letters which are no longer found in the collection.
  The remainder of correspondence consists of letters to Alexander from fellow artists, patrons, museums, arts organizations, and friends. Significant correspondents include Charles Dana Gibson, Florence Levy, Frederick Remington, Robert Louis Stevenson, Henry James, John La Farge, Francis Davis Millet, and Andrew Carnegie. These and other significant correspondents are noted in the folder listing. Letters dated after Alexander's death in 1915 are addressed to Elizabeth Alexander, with a single letter addressed to the Alexanders' son James.
  A number of sketches by Alexander are found in his letters from Europe dated from 1877 to 1880. There are also scattered illustrated letters and an Illustrated letter from Ivan P. Pranishnikoff is found from 1898. Additional types of records found include scattered receipts and clippings.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated correspondence filed at the beginning of the series. Additional correspondence is found in Scrapbooks. See Scrapbook series description and folder listing for more details. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Undated Correspondence, Adams to Garland (Box 1, Folder 10)
    (Correspondents include John White Alexander, W.K. Austin, Charles Curran, M.K. Gage, Charles Dana Gibson, and H. Garland)
  - Undated Correspondence, Johnston to Whistler (Box 1, Folder 11)
    (Correspondents include Ella Bond Johnston, O. Latrobe, Florence Levy, E.L. Ryerson, Ebin R. Smith, Robert Louis Stevenson, Harry Watrous, and James McNeill Whistler)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1874 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1875; (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 13-20)
    (ink drawing found)
  - Correspondence, 1876; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
  - Correspondence, 1877; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
    (sketches found)
  - Correspondence, 1878; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-34)
  - Correspondence, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1882 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1883-1886 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1887; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-42)
    (Correspondents include Harry Alexander, John Burroughs, and Henry James)
  - Correspondence, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - correspondence, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    (Correspondents include Ministry of Art Education in France and Elizabeth Alexander)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1895 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    (Correspondents include M.R. Blair, J.J. Cowan, Lydia E. Grosvenor Davis, Mayor F. Grimani of Venice, William Turner Dannat, and Puvis de Chavannes)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1900 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    (Correspondents include Frantz Jourdain, Fr. Linley Sanbourne, and Cowan family members)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    (Correspondents include Samuel Huey, Andrew Carnegie, John La Farge, the Pan American Exposition of 1901, Princeton University, Mabel Carleton Gage, Homer Gage, Hester Knowles, and Harper Brothers to Elizabeth Alexander)
  - Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    (Includes many letters from John White Alexander written in Boston; also letters from Anne Bradley)
  - Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    (Correspondents include Anne Bradley, R.D. Alexander, Carnegie Library, H.N. Matzen, F.D. Millet, and D. Webster King)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    (Correspondents include Stanford White, Charles Dana Gibson, Joseph Pennell, Alfred East, and John La Farge)
  - Correspondence, 1909; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
    (Includes many letters of congratulations written to Alexander on his election as president of the National Academy of Design. Also contains a note indicating that several letters in this folder were removed from Alexander's scrapbook of 1909. See Scrapbooks for more information. Correspondents include Albert Sternan, John W. Beatty, Charles Dana Gibson, Florence (probably Levy), Elbert Baldwin, Edward Robsinon, Samuel Swift, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Anna M. Clarke, William Laurel Harris, Harrison S. Morris, Thomas Hastings, Frank D. Millet, C. Russell, Jeannette Gilder, Robert Underwood Johnson, John La Farge, Fred Crowninshield, Leon Dabo, Henri Martin, and Edward Bok.)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    (Correspondents include Andrew Carnegie, Houston Lowe, Birge Harrison, William Hyde, M.A. Dixon, Yale University regarding an honorary degree, Alfred East, John F. Weir, and DeWitt Parshall)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    (Correspondents include Edward Redfield, W.D. Howells, Potter Palmer, Geo. Dudley Seymour, Mary Hearn Greims, Josephine L. Goodyear, Geo. Peabody Wetmore, and Leslie J. Skelton.)
  - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    (Correspondents include George Hearn, Hugo Reisinger, C. Grant La Farge, Leslie Skelton, Trinity Church, Fred Crowninshield, Geo. Dudley Seymour, the Panama-Pacific Exposition, Timothy Cole, and Edward Redfield)
  - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    (Correspondents include Francis Newton, George Hopkins, Cass Gilbert, H.C. Mansfield, Robert Underwood Johnson, and Woodrow Wilson)
  - Correspondence, 1915; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 58-62)
    (Letters to Alexander are found from Campbell Cooper, Carl Becker, Henry B. Snell, and Douglas Volk. Letters of condolence to the Alexanders are found from Charles Dana Gibson, E.J. Allen, E.A.S. Clarke, Maude (probably Adams), Ernest Peix (probably Peixotto), Geo. Wharton Edwards, Edward Woods, Robert Abbe, Robert Underwood Johnson, Franklin Babbitt, Edwin H. Blashfield, Harrison Morris, J. Alden Weir, Janet Van Buskirk, Edwin Baldwin, J. Henry Harper, William Laurel Harris, Adolph Lewisohn, Earl Stetson Crawford, Ernest T. Rosen, C.H. Russell, Frances M. Ward, S.H. Church, Robert De Forest, John H. Finley, John F. Weir, Ben Foster, William Bailey Faxon, William Walton, Charles H. Caffin, Bruce Crane, Herbert Adams, Ed Phelps, Elizabeth W. Roberts, Augusta H.S. Gaudens, Frederic Allen Whiting, Florence Levy, John Beatty, Harry Watrous, and C. Powell Minnigerode.)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    (Correspondents include Howard Mansfield, Jane Potter Russell, J. Howland Hunt, Robert Underwood Johnson, John Beatty, John H. Finley, May Allen, Cooper Union, National Arts Club, M. MacDowell, N. H. Carpenter, and S.H. Church)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    (Correspondents include Carroll Beckwith, whose letter includes a photographer of her portrait by Alexander, Francis Wilson, Leila Mechlin, Edward Bok, Jean MacLane, Julian Clarence Levi, and W.H. Holmes)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1929 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    (Correspondents include R.M. MacIntyre, Alex Simpson, Edwin Blashfield, DuBon and Dorothy, L.M. Lockhart, E.C. Babcock, Homer Saint Gaudens, Grace Vanamee, Walter Crittenden, and William Henry Fox.)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    (Correspondents include William Barclay Parsons, Gertrude Herdle Moore, Norbert Heerman, Horace Moran, and Edwin Blashfield)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    (Correspondents include William Weldon, Norbert Heerman, Harrison Morris, Agnes Holden, and the Museum of the City of New York.)
  - Correspondence, circa 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    (Correspondents include Homer Saint Gaudens, Carnegie Magazine, John O'Connor, C. Bernard Shea, and Hobart Nichols.)
  - Correspondence, Envelopes, 1874-1904 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Typescript Copies of Selected Correspondence (1912-1916), undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Associations and Memberships, circa 1897-1918; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1